<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[AvidDabbler Blog]]></title><description><![CDATA[Maping communities and measuring what matters]]></description><link>https://blog.walterkjenkins.com</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 01:55:19 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Hosting Static Sites on AWS]]></title><description><![CDATA[Intro As I expressed in my last post, there were a number of different options that AWS offers to get up and running on a budget when…]]></description><link>https://blog.walterkjenkins.com/190826-Hosting-a-Static-Site-on-s3/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.walterkjenkins.com/190826-Hosting-a-Static-Site-on-s3/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Intro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I expressed in my last post, there were a number of different options that AWS offers to get up and running on a budget when hosting a static website, but at the end of the day I will be going the S3 / Cloudfront way of hosting and routing. This post will go through the following steps in a logical way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hosting your files through AWS S3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connecting your files to be accessible through url via Cloudfront.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use CodeBuild to connect your files to a GitHub Repo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure a custom domain to your project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;MAKE SURE THAT YOU ARE CREATING THESE ALL WITHIN THE SAME REGION.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Set Up Your S3 Bucket&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the first thing that you need to know about setting up your website is where you need to store these files. &lt;a href=&quot;https://s3.console.aws.amazon.com/s3&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;S3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is the most common way to store file on AWS securely. Think of S3 as your secure Dropbbox. Or that Dropbox is using S3? Anyway, S3 is going to be where you are going to be storing all of your static website files. In this section we are just going to focus on getting the bucket made public. You wont need to worry about getting anything moved over into the bucket as we will configure it to sync with your GitHub in the next section. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Go to your AWS Console and go to the S3 section of AWS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. create bucket with website name minus &lt;em&gt;www&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Go inside the bucket and the make public by going to the permissions tab and then click the &lt;em&gt;Block Public Access&lt;/em&gt; button then click edit and turn them all off. Then save.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. In the same permissions tab click the &lt;em&gt;Bucket Policy&lt;/em&gt; button. Then paste the following rule in the code editor and configuring it for the bucket that you just created.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;gatsby-highlight&quot; data-language=&quot;text&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;{
    &amp;quot;Version&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;2012-10-17&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;Statement&amp;quot;: [
        {
            &amp;quot;Sid&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;PublicReadGetObject&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;Effect&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;Allow&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;Principal&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;*&amp;quot;,
            &amp;quot;Action&amp;quot;: [
                &amp;quot;s3:GetObject&amp;quot;
            ],
            &amp;quot;Resource&amp;quot;: [
                &amp;quot;arn:aws:s3:::example-bucket/*&amp;quot;
            ]
        }
    ]
}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. In that same window go to the properties tab and then click &lt;em&gt;Static Website Hosting&lt;/em&gt;. Click &lt;em&gt;Use this Bucket to Host a Website&lt;/em&gt; set the index document to &lt;em&gt;index.html&lt;/em&gt; or whatever you set it up as in your static site. Click Save.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Create CodePipeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, we need some file to host. These files have to come from somewhere. Sure you could have just uploaded some files to your S3 and called it a night, but you want to put the work in you want to be able to just forget that you have to do that. You need &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/codepipeline/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CodePipeline&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. CodePipeline is a great way to work with your code from a project that you want to host somewhere on GitHub, but also store for hosting on AWS. What this next section will do is help you manage the connection between your GitHub branch and your S3 so that whenever you make a change to your specified branch it will push out an update to your S3 bucket where you have your website files hosted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Name the pipeline after your bucket for simplicity.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. new service role&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Advanced settings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;- Custom Location (Select the S3 bucket that you want to connect to as they need to be in the same location.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;- Default AWS Managed Key&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Next&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Set your source provider to GitHub
**Allow AWS to access GitHub
**Select the Repository and Branch
**Use GitHub Webhooks
**Next
**If your site is just static files you can just skip build stage, but if it in React or Gatsby you will need to add the build script in here
**Set Deploy provider to Amazon S3
**Select the bucket
**Select extract files before deploy - This will allow for your files to be hosted in a readable format instead of all zipped up in a single file.
**Next
**Create Pipeline&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Set up AWS Certificate Manager&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go to Certificate Manager in the AWS console&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;type in walterkjenkins.com and www.walterkjenkins.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;copy over CNAME data to domains.google.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;wait for validation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Set up CloundFront to connect to S3 Bucket&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Origin Domain Name: select our bucket generated public domain, in this case &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;www.walterkjenkins.com.s3.amazonaws.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, but you could set it up as &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;%your_site%.s3.amazonaws.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Origin Path: leave this blank&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Origin ID: by default, this field will be auto-generated by CloudFront, you can custom it as you want&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restrict Bucket Access: yes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;alternative CNAME walterkjenkins.com www.walterkjenkins.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Origin Access Identity: Create a New Identity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comment: www.walterkjenkins.com-cloudfront&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grant Read Permissions on Bucket: Yes, Update Bucket Policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Default Root Object: index.html&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leave the rest filled default value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click Create Distribution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go back to cloudfront&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;edit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attach the custom ssl certificate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;save&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;DNS Configuration&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go back to domains.google.com&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add the www and * with the cloudfront.net address&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Sources:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/faun/deploy-static-website-to-amazon-s3-from-github-repository-3f1245d2a780&quot;&gt;Deploy Static Website to Amazon S3 from Github Repository&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@kyle.galbraith/how-to-host-a-website-on-s3-without-getting-lost-in-the-sea-e2b82aa6cd38&quot;&gt;How to Host a Website on S3 Without Getting Lost in the Sea&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@aashari&quot;&gt;Deploy Static Website to Amazon S3 from Github Repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[AWS and the Three Bears]]></title><description><![CDATA[Intro Getting your site hosted can be a huge hassle. There are a ton of options out there, but if you want to keep costs down choosing the…]]></description><link>https://blog.walterkjenkins.com/190825-AWS-and-the-Three-Bears/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.walterkjenkins.com/190825-AWS-and-the-Three-Bears/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h1&gt;Intro&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting your site hosted can be a huge hassle. There are a ton of options out there, but if you want to keep costs down choosing the next draggy-droppy solutions can get expensive and you may not want to chose a newer technology as you may have some problems (as I did) when something goes wrong. However, there is rarely the documentation that clearly spells out ONE way of doing things (but really that’s not how we learn anyway is it?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first started out trying to figure out how to host my portfolio site and blog I did a ton of research on how I could host the damn thing and what I wanted to do all while learning a little about hosting. The initial goals of the project were as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host a website and do so for less than a cup of coffee a month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Allow for me to update the site through a GitHub repository.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a custom domain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat the process under a subdomain for my blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Problems with Hosting on GitHub&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;I know that I can host a blog and and portfolio site on GitHub pages for free&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; that would defeat the purpose of the project. I also knew that I wanted to be able to attach my project to something that would allow me to grow within a platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had heard of a number of different options out there as far as cloud providers are concerned, but I ended up going with AWS just because it seems to be the most widely supported cloud platform and seemed like a good introductory project in getting involved into the ecosystem for hosting files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Options within AWS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is probably the most frustrating part of the whole process for me. AWS has so many ways of doing things and there are so many different platforms out there that seemed great, but I eventually narrowed it down to 3 different options all of which I got to different levels of befor bailing to another, but I am proud to say that 3rd times the charm and that I am happy with my final choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all technology these days there is an array of trade offs that often sound constantly like one old fable or another. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Today’s Story is AWS and the Three Bears.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Papa Bear Solution: EC2, Lightsail, and Apache&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first started this process I wanted to do it all. I wanted to be up to my elbows in documentation, I wanted to host the files, manage the server, keep up with all of the dependencies. So I started working with &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/lightsail/&quot;&gt;AWS Lightsail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The benefit of working with lightsail is that this solution is configured exactly the way that you like. I started off by getting the EC2 instance configured. I ended up using Ubuntu, getting Apache installed, struggling through documentation about hosting files. However, at the end of the day I couldn’t get it to work. BUT I learned a lot about EC2, improved my command line skills and figured out that this is not the solution for me. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I was starting some startup and wanted to take the time to build something from scratch I would go with something along these lines, but at the end of the day this is too much of my time that I will never get back and I need to focus on other things in life other than remaining in config file hell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Baby Bear: AWS Amplify&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really though that &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws-amplify.github.io/&quot;&gt;AWS Amplify&lt;/a&gt; was going to be the solution… and it was for about a week. AWS Amplify was great. No command line, direct connection to GitHub. All in all I know how to get something up and running in about 5 minutes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AWS Amplify is a new service on AWS. So they are still kicking the tires on this. When I first uploaded my site it was great. Initialization was a breeze. Load was fast(ish). However, I went to go add another project today. My app is missing from the Amplify dashboard, but is somehow is still being hosted and I am still being charged. So my experience with it has been mixed to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Mama Bear: S3 Buckets, Cloudfront and Code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day I have decided that the best solution is of medium configuration. It is an integration of 3 well established solutions in AWS. &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/s3/&quot;&gt;S3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/cloudfront/&quot;&gt;Cloudfront&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/codebuild/&quot;&gt;CodeBuild&lt;/a&gt;. S3 will handle holding all of your data, Cloudfront will handle routing your data to url and CodeBuild will work with your repository to make sure that it updates when you update your GitHub via Webhooks. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The price of my final solution should be extremely affordable as my site at this moment is only about 5mb in total. I don’t have any information about how much it will cost me, but I will update this in the future to let you know how much I am getting charged a month on average. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out my next post for how I configured the whole thing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[GitHub Portfolio Builder]]></title><description><![CDATA[The GitHub Portfolio Builder was designed to work with porfolio sites to easily pull down data from your GitHub Repository Thumbnails This…]]></description><link>https://blog.walterkjenkins.com/190817-github-portfolio-builder/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://blog.walterkjenkins.com/190817-github-portfolio-builder/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;The GitHub Portfolio Builder was designed to work with porfolio sites to easily pull down data from your GitHub Repository&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Thumbnails&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project has been configured to have the thumbnail photo located in the master root folder of your repo called “thumbnail.PNG”. Locattion can be edited by going in the getData() return function and changing up the thumbnail template literal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;thumbnail: `https://raw.githubusercontent.com/${usr}/${repo}/master/thumbnail.PNG`;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Profiles / User&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first line of code you can set your default username up for GitHub. IF you by any chance have a project that you want to include that does NOT use your default username. You can add in the username in the setupArr by adding an element to the array. This is only required if you want to use a different user profile project for whatever reason. By default the user is set to &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;user&lt;/code&gt; for the constructor function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Description &amp;#x26; Technology Formatting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Configuring on GigHub:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have set up my repositories descriptions a specific way for this project to work. I have inculded 2 nessessary sections to run this by editing my repository description on the GitHub page. This is done by setting up a default separator in the description as &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;||&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;fetchedData&lt;/code&gt; brings in the full description and then splits it into an array. By default this split is set to &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;||&lt;/code&gt;, but can be changed on at &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;split&lt;/code&gt;. Below is an example of how I formated my &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;Backyard Chickens&lt;/code&gt; repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 590px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/5c7bb1101bcd19d6cc0888c022f54c74/c1e1e/github_description.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 21.37862137862138%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAECAYAAACOXx+WAAAACXBIWXMAABYlAAAWJQFJUiTwAAAAs0lEQVQY02WQ24rDMAxE8//fWCj70pQQS7Lk2JGdMlVS2F3ow2F0Qxo0kRjuD8HP0nCb68XMjj6OL7wPjOMFzornsqJsDSsJ1AoSS+QVU82EIgTbHLk0lOqwUrF7R9v9i9oa9tBz8RGM/8TRqWwbRDKEGYkI/KsCCiX6q3PMJdYg5rWEU7tUckZW/ThcUsa8EFTtsziaGk0WQT5js0vlzC2Ol46kO1Z1sDko8N7D3Yi3DLwB5sUz2pMqKNcAAAAASUVORK5CYII=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;image of repo descripttion&quot;
        title=&quot;image of repo descripttion&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/5c7bb1101bcd19d6cc0888c022f54c74/b9e4f/github_description.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/5c7bb1101bcd19d6cc0888c022f54c74/cf440/github_description.png 148w,
/static/5c7bb1101bcd19d6cc0888c022f54c74/d2d38/github_description.png 295w,
/static/5c7bb1101bcd19d6cc0888c022f54c74/b9e4f/github_description.png 590w,
/static/5c7bb1101bcd19d6cc0888c022f54c74/f9b6a/github_description.png 885w,
/static/5c7bb1101bcd19d6cc0888c022f54c74/c1e1e/github_description.png 1001w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Description&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Technology&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Implementations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have implemented this GitHub code to build my own personal portfolio site so that I can easily update this information when I know someone is going to be looking at my site. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Check it out @ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.walterkjenkins.com/#portfolio&quot;&gt;walterkjenkins.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>